<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true account of the behaviour, confession, and execution of William Charley and Ann Scot, who received sentence of death on the 27th of August last, at Justice-Hall in the Old-Bayly, and were executed at Tyburn on Friday the 4th of this instant September 1685. : As also a brief account of the seven other persons, who received sentence of death with them, but before execution found mercy in a gracious reprieve, viz. John Thompson, Thomas Draper, Thomas Glanister, Cathrine Baucer, Cassandra Widdows, Ellenor Steel, and Elizabeth Hacker.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06205</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R226729</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52612460</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52612460</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179682</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06205)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179682)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2796:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true account of the behaviour, confession, and execution of William Charley and Ann Scot, who received sentence of death on the 27th of August last, at Justice-Hall in the Old-Bayly, and were executed at Tyburn on Friday the 4th of this instant September 1685. : As also a brief account of the seven other persons, who received sentence of death with them, but before execution found mercy in a gracious reprieve, viz. John Thompson, Thomas Draper, Thomas Glanister, Cathrine Baucer, Cassandra Widdows, Ellenor Steel, and Elizabeth Hacker.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Mallet in Black-Horse-Alley in Fleet-street, near Fleet-Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Printed in double columns.</note>
                  <note>At end: "This may be printd, R.L.S. September the 4th 1685."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charley, William.</term>
               <term>Scot, Ann.</term>
               <term>Theft --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Executions and executioners --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:179682:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A TRUE ACCOUNT OF THE Behaviour, Confeſſion, AND EXECUTION OF <hi>William Charley</hi> and <hi>Ann Scot,</hi> Who Received Sentence of Death on the 27th. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, at JUSTICE-HALL in the <hi>OLD-BAYLY,</hi> and were Executed at TYBURN On <hi>Friday</hi> the 4th. of this Inſtant <hi>September</hi> 1685.</head>
            <head type="sub">As alſo a Brief Account of the Seven other perſons, who received Sentence of Death with them, but before Execution found mercy in a Gracious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieve, <hi>viz. John Thompſon, Thomas Draper. Thomas Glaniſter, Cathrine Baucer, Caſſandra Widdows, Ellenor Steel,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth Hacker.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>STill it appears, notwithſtanding the many precedent Examples Juſtice has made of Offenders, that divers are beſotted to that degree, or deluded by the wiles and Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Enemy of mankind; that regardleſs of their Safety, Lives, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, they will raſhly run them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Ruin and Diſgrace, neither fear of Shame nor Severity being of force ſufficient to keep them within the Bounds of Honeſty and civil Behaviour, nor to make them look back and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the danger they are in, till it is too late to Retrive the ſad diſaſter, then, and but then, they are content to open their Eyes, and inform themſelves how they have been intic'd and drawn away how eaſily they have conſented to the perſwaſions of wicked perſons, whom <hi>Satan</hi> has laid as ſnares in their way to undo them, as will more evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the following Relation, in which is contained; more eſpecially the Crimes, Manner of Behaviour and Confeſſion of two Perſons cut off by the Hand of Juſtice, in the prime and ſtrength of their days, as it was obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and taken from themſelves in <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVilliam Charley,</hi> Tryed the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Seſſions, holden at <hi>Juſtice-Hall</hi> in the <hi>Old-Bayly</hi> upon an Indictment of Felony and Burglary, Committed on and in the Ware Houſe of one Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Loveday,</hi> Scituate in the Pariſh of St. <hi>Michaels London:</hi> It appeared that Cloath had been ſtolen thence to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:179682:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>the value 120 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> and that upon ſearch, part of it was found in <hi>Crouders-Well-Alley</hi> in <hi>Jeven ſtreet;</hi> and upon further inquirie it was proved to be brought thither by <hi>Charley</hi> and others, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe other percels of Cloath, that had been carried out and diſpoſed of, and he having been formerly burnt in the hand, no perſon appearing to give teſtimony on his behal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, he was found Guilty; when upon his Conviction he became exceeding ſad, imagining as he ſince confeſſed no mercy would be allowed him, ſince he had refuſed to take warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by his former puniſhment. The day following, being the 27th. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, he with Eight other Offenders re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Sentence of Death, and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Newgate</hi> in order to prepare himſelf for another World, his offences having render'd him incapable of a much longer continuance in this; where (upon his firſt arrival) he betook himſelf to his Devotion, imploring the God of mercys, to have mercy upon his Soul; and that in compaſſion thereto, he would be pleaſed to give him a heart to repent: After theſe and ſuch like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, he proceeded to declare he had been a great ſinner, tho' but a young man not exceeding 25. Years of Age: Being asked what his former buſineſs was, and how he ſpent his time before he fell to ſuch unlawful courſes; he ſaid he was born of honeſt Parents in <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventry,</hi> who uſed their faithful endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to qualifie him by learning and what elſe was convenient for buſineſs that might render him credible, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able him to live in the World; and that as ſoon as he was of Years capable for Employment, put him Apprentice to one <hi>Mr. Hix,</hi> a Callender in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and furniſhed him with all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient neceſſaries; but he, after he had a while faithfully ſerved the ſaid <hi>Mr. Hix,</hi> finding opportunity to ramble a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad ſorted himſelf with bad Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which by degrees drew him to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect his buſineſs and in the end to ſteal, the better to ſupport and maintain his Extravagance: Being asked what was his firſt Fact in that Nature, he replyed, ſtealing a conſiderable quantity of <hi>Blew</hi> Cloath which he was intruſted with by his Maſter, or at leaſt had the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of taking it, he being at that time a Porter to a Drapers Shop, which Cloath he diſpoſed of at a ſmall value, but the Theft being found out and proved againſt him; He was about Four Years ſince burnt in the Hand for that Felony, and Caſhired from his Service, after which; ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling up and down he fell in Love with a Servant Maid, and to mannage Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilely his Courtſhip (being deſtitute of any Lawful Employ, whereby he could ſupport himſelf as he deſired) he ſaid he betook himſelf to unlawful courſes ſtealing (as opportunity gave leave) Goods at ſundry times from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers perſons, ſpending the ſmall value he had ſold them at (being for the moſt part under hand) upon the Woman he ſo earneſtly deſired; being asked how he found himſelf as to another State, he replyed, he was very ſenſible of his Latter End, deſiring nothing more than that he might live long enough to make his peace with God, whom he had offended in ſo high a Nature, and whoſe Mercys and opportunities of Grace he had ſlighted and rejected, for which he was heartily ſorry, hoping that it was not too late to repent him of the <hi>Evil of his ways,</hi> deſiring ſuch as came to viſit him, that they would in Chriſtian Charity pray for him, that God might give him a true Repentance, earneſtly deſiring that his misfortune might be of Efficacy to prevail upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers not to give way to deceivers and deluding perſons, to intice them under any ſpecious pretence whatſoever, to give up their mind to Idleneſs and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; but above all, he deſired that all young men Apprentices would ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weigh his condition, and conſider by what degrees he was brought to be an Object of Miſery, which he ſaid he well hoped would be a means to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue and retain them within the Bounds of Apprentices, <hi>viz.</hi> in minding the buſineſs they were intruſted with, in pleaſing their Maſters, and giving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſobriety and moderation, but eſpecially to avoid evil company, for that had ruined him, and is indeed the Root of wickedneſs, ſhame &amp; diſgrace.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:179682:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>To thoſe that came to viſit him he was very reſpectful, giving great attention to ſuch advice as was given him, relating to a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for Death, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued very ſenſible and penitent during his being in <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ann Scot,</hi> Convicted the ſame Seſſions with the former, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Sentence of Death, upon Evidence that ſhe had Feloniouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken a Flower'd Mantua-Gown, a Sattin-Petticoat and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Goods, out of the Houſe of <hi>James Marmion,</hi> Scituate in the Pariſh of St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> and not being capable of ſaying any thing material for her ſelf; ſhe upon her return to <hi>Newgate</hi> became ſad as the former, being frequently obſerved to wring her Hands and Sigh, ſaying, ſhe was the unhappieſt Woman alive wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe had never been Born, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to have fallen into ſo unhappy a Condition: As for the place of her Birth, ſhe ſaid it was in the County of <hi>Down</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> being brought up there to work divers curious Works with the Needle, but leaving her Parents, and coming over upon a ſlight oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, the chiefeſt Motive being to ſee this Country, and ſhe after a while brought to ſome neceſſity betook her ſelf to Imbrodering, and found a conſiderable Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, living as a ſingle Woman, in <hi>White</hi>'s-<hi>Alley</hi> in <hi>Chancery Lane,</hi> working there very hard, but that ſort of buſineſs failing, ſhe fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to looſe and idle Company, who encouraged her in Leudneſs, and altogether took her off from her Employment to follow unlawful Courſes, as well Debauchery, and Proſtitution, as plfering and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Matters tending to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud and Injuſtice, which by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees had imboldened her to the height of Wickedneſs in which ſhe was overtaken: She ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a year ſince ſhe was Tryed for a Cravat valued at 3 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> which was ſtole, but there being no other Evidence than that ſhe had paun'd it upon the account of another, ſhe was acquitted, yet was not ſo wiſe as to lay that narrow eſcape to her Heart, nor to take up, and reſt her ſelf ſatisfied therewith, wherefore what had ſince befallen her, ſhe ſaid was juſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if ſhe muſt dye ſhe would bear it patiently, tho' it happened untimely; ſhe not being above 34. Years of Age, yet the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of that time ſhe had miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imployed in ſining againſt her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; few known ſins that ſhe was capable of Acting, Murther ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, ſhe having been a ſtranger to her, yet ſhe hoped God would not lay them to her Charge in her laſt extremity, but out of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his Mercys, accept her imperfect Repentance, being ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed whether ſhe found her ſelf diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to imbrace the penalty of the Law, puniſhing with Death ſuch has had offended in the like Nature as ſhe had done, her reply was, that if ſhe might live ſhe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped ſhe ſhould employ her time for the future to a better advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, but if not, God's Will be done; and ſo continued in often Prayer to her ſelf, ſeeming very
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179682:3"/>attentive to good and wholeſome advice relating to her immortal well-fare, expreſſing her deſire to be inſtructed therein, as much as Conveniency and Opportunity would permit, and in that State of Penitence during the Reſpit in <hi>Newgate</hi> ſhe was very diligent.</p>
            <p>Seven other Perſons lay like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe under the ſame Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as <hi>Catharine Baucer, Caſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra Widdows,</hi> for being concerned with <hi>Ann Scot,</hi> in Robbing Mr. <hi>Marmion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Draper,</hi> for ſtealing a Gelding, valued at 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> from one <hi>William Watſon,</hi> of the Pariſh of St. <hi>Sepulchres,</hi> on the 14th of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Thompſon,</hi> for breaking the Houſe of <hi>Thomas Temple</hi> of the Pariſh of St. <hi>Michaels Wood-ſtreet</hi> on the 21th. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, and ſtealing thence 7. Napkins value 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 2 Handkerchiefs value 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and other Linnen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Glaniſter,</hi> for breaking open the Houſe of <hi>John Clark,</hi> in the Pariſh of St. <hi>Andrews Holborn</hi> on the 2<abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, and ſteal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 3 Stuff-Coats, value 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 2 pair of Breeches value 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Goods of value.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elizabeth Hacker,</hi> for ſtealing a Chamblet Cloak value 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> out of the Chamber of one <hi>Alexander Hulſton</hi> of the Parſh of St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews Holbourn,</hi> on the 27th. of <hi>July.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe, in hopes of their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment and being reclaimed, found the Royal Mercy &amp; Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Compaſſion in a Gracious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieve for a longer Life, having before expreſſed their Sorrowful ſenſe of their ſad Condition to which they had brought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by breaking the known Laws, and forfeiting their Lives to Juſtice.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Friday</hi> the 4th. of <hi>Auguſt, William Charley</hi> and <hi>Ann Scot</hi> were put in a Cart, and conveyed to <hi>Tyburn,</hi> the place of Execution where they were Executed as the Law in ſuch Caſes requires.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>This may be Printd, R. L. S.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>September</hi> the 4th. 1685.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>E. Mallet</hi> in <hi>Black-Horſe-Alley</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> near <hi>Fleet-Bridge,</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
